Inventory of the John W. Lewis and Lewis P. Olds Papers 1808-1902
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
John W. Lewis and Lewis P. Olds Papers 1808-1900s1840-1879
Special Collections Research Center
01/Mss. Acc. 2010.022
1.00
Collection consists of the papers of three Southerners, dating predominantly from the 19th century. John W. Lewis lived in Virginia, Mississippi, and North Carolina and the portion of the collection from this Methodist minister and farmer includes references to religion including sermons, farming, and slavery. Lewis P. Olds was a North Carolina lawyer and politician and the collection includes evidence of his career as well as poetry and short stories he wrote. The remainder of the collection is schoolwork of Sally Latting from 1808 and unattributed photographs and a recipe book.
Lewis, John W., [1808]-1885; Latting, Sally; Olds, Lewis P. arrangement
Administrative Information
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open to all researchers.
Acquisition Information
The materials were acquired by Special Collections Research Center from Tim Abbott on 01/20/2010.
Biographical Note
John W. Lewis was raised in Randolph County, North Carolina. In 1833, at around the age of 25, Lewis entered the Virginia Conference of Methodist ministers. His 50+ year career as a pastor took him from Virginia to Mississippi and eventually back to his home state of North Carolina. Lewis was a slave-owning member of the Methodist Episcopal Church, South (MEC-S) offshoot that split from the main Methodist Episcopal Church due to differing views on the issue of slavery. He died on May 23, 1885. Further information about this individual or organization may be available in the Special Collections Research Center Wiki: http://scrc.swem.wm.edu/wiki/index.php/John_W._Lewis
Scope and Contents
Collection consists of the papers of three Southerners, dating predominantly from the 19th century. John W. Lewis lived in Virginia, Mississippi, and North Carolina and the portion of the collection from this Methodist minister and farmer includes references to religion including sermons, farming, and slavery. Lewis P. Olds was a North Carolina lawyer and politician and the collection includes evidence of his career as well as poetry and short stories he wrote. The remainder of the collection is schoolwork of Sally Latting from 1808 and unattributed photographs and a recipe book.
Arrangement of Materials
This collection is arranged into 3 series: Series 1: John W. Lewis; Series 2: Lewis P. Olds; Series 3: Miscellaneous.
Additional Information
Index Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Genre/Form of Material:
Broadsides; Correspondence; Photographs; Recipes; Sermons
Geographic Name:
North Carolina--History--19th century--Sources.; North Carolina--Social life and customs--19th century.; Virginia--History--19th century--Sources
Topical Term:
Poems; Slavery--North Carolina--History.; Slavery--Virginia--History--19th century.; Virginia--Social life and customs--19th century
Detailed Description of the Collection
- John W. Lewis, 1840-1885; id67450
  - id67453 (Box 1)
    - John W. Lewis Correspondence, 1840-1885; id67454 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - John W. Lewis Correspondence, 1840-1885; id67455 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - John W. Lewis Personal Papers, 1840-1885; id67456 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Lewis P. Olds, 1840-1900; id67451
  - id67457 (Box 1)
    - Lewis P. Olds Correspondence, 1840-1900; id67459 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Lewis P. Olds Correspondence, 1840-1900; id67460 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Lewis P. Olds Correspondence, 1840-1900; id67461 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Lewis P. Olds Poetry, 1840-1900; id67462 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Lewis P. Olds Poetry, 1840-1900; id67463 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Lewis P. Olds Poetry, 1840-1900; id67464 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - id67458 (Box 2)
    - Lewis P. Olds Poetry, 1840-1900; id67465 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Lewis P. Olds Poetry, 1840-1900; id70868 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Miscellaneous, 1808-circa 1900; id67452
  - id67466 (Box 2)
    - Sally Latting Schoolwork, 1808; id67467 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Photographs, circa 1800-1900; id67468 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Recipe Books, circa 1800-1900; id67469 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Papers, circa 1840-1870; id65214